

MEHMET AKİF **TÜTÜNCÜ**

Lead Software Engineer

+31 6 87 98 68 87

m.akif.tutuncu@gmail.com

Utrecht, Netherlands

<u>akif.dev</u>

github.com/makiftutuncu

linkedin.com/in/makiftutuncu

Over 10 years of professional experience in backend development with a specialization in JVM technologies such as Scala, Kotlin, and Java. Provided consulting services to global companies, emphasizing object-oriented and functional programming. Strong background in CI/CD, testing, databases, cloud infrastructure, microservices, and software architecture. Developed open-source tools for developers, gave voluntary lectures and presented at conferences and meetups. Interests include traveling, cooking, and rock/metal music.

SKILLS

Programming

Functional Programming, Go, Java,
 Kotlin, Object Oriented Programming,
 Reactive Programming, Scala, TypeScript

Frameworks & Libraries

Akka, Cats, Circe, Http4s, Micronaut,
 Play Framework, Quarkus, Quill, React,
 Spring Boot, Spring Framework, ZIO

Databases & Data Stores

 Cassandra, DynamoDB, Elasticsearch, Hazelcast, Memcached, MongoDB, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, Redshift, Zookeeper

Cloud & DevOps

 AWS, Azure, Docker, Google Cloud Platform, Kubernetes

Tools & Methodologies

 ActiveMQ, Git, Gradle, GraphQL, JUnit, Kafka, Kanban, Maven, TestContainers, SBT, ScalaTest, SCRUM, Specs2

WORK EXPERIENCE

Lead Software Engineer @ iO

iodigital.com / Utrecht, Netherlands / 12-2022 to Now

- Consultant at Rabobank
 - Led development in a team of 6 developers, building an internal functional documentation portal for Rabo Online Platform, supporting 69 web apps, 250 squads, over 1500 engineers, and 1200 applications
 - Migrated 4 backend services into a new architecture that allows for extending the functionality of the portal
 - Integrated with Azure AI services in 3 months to build a smart assistant capable of answering questions based on documentation on the portal
- Tech-Lead at iO
 - Presented at 3 conferences, made 3 public meetups and 2 internal workshops
 - Co-authored 1 article for the company blog
 - Conducted 15 recruitment interviews and reviews
 - Started 3 open-source projects
 - Mentored team members

Senior Software Engineer @ Scalac

scalac.io / Istanbul, Turkey / 11-2021 to 10-2022

- Consultant at Conduktor
 - Migrated legacy Java APIs to a new Scala service, encompassing approximately 50 endpoints
 - Introduced an automated mechanism to verify correctness by comparing responses from both sets of endpoints
 - Developed an admin portal for the Conduktor Platform, offering management capabilities for Kafka clusters with easy-to-use user interfaces

EDUCATION

Izmir Institute of Technology

Computer Engineering 09-2009 to 06-2014

PUBLICATIONS

Videos of talks and presentations from conferences/meetups:

tinyurl.com/makiftutuncu-talks

- Blog: dev.to/makiftutuncu
- Blog about Scala in Turkish:
 makiftutuncu.wordpress.com
- One of the first blogs about Android in Turkish: <u>androidce.blogspot.com</u>

PROJECTS

- <u>periodik</u>: Read-only property delegate that can provide a value refreshed periodically
- <u>spring-boot-crud</u>: Opinionated, RESTful and generic CRUD operations for Spring Boot applications
- effect: Functional effect library in Scala
- <u>e</u>: Zero-dependency error handling library
- <u>bookstore</u>: Project demonstrating automated testing on backend
- Muezzin: Android application and server

LANGUAGES

- Turkish (Native)
- English (Fluent)
- Dutch (Beginner)

CERTIFICATIONS

- Agility: Team Accelerator
- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner
- Complete Guide to Elasticsearch
- AWS Certified Solutions Architect -Associate

Senior Software Engineer @ Numbrs

numbrs.com / Istanbul, Turkey / 11-2020 to 10-2021

- Developed new features for the Numbrs application in Personal Finance Management Team
- Implemented backend services utilizing Go, Java, Scala, Kafka and Cassandra
- Created the "Insights" feature, delivering 7 unique, smart and actionable insights to users based on demographic information and bank transactions

Senior Software Engineer @ sahibinden

sahibinden.com / Istanbul, Turkey / 08-2019 to 10-2020

- Focused on domains including search, promotions, and categories in Search Team
- Led a 6-month project to automate the updating of geo and location data
- Integrated with a third-party data provider and performed 4 data migrations in a production environment with no downtime, pioneering the use of Kotlin in a Java codebase for the project

Software Engineer @ VNGRS

vngrs.com / Istanbul, Turkey / 06-2017 to 09-2019

- Consultant at Socrata Team
 - Improved the Open Data Platform, containing about 20 backend projects
 - Created an activity log service for auditing all platform activities
- Consultant at Beam
 - Conducted a cloud migration from Sydney to Dubai
 - Stabilized and adapted the mobile payment system to work in Duhai
 - Implemented "Ticketless Parking", integrating car parking payments with Beam
- Consultant at MAF Properties Team
 - Joined the kick-off process for a rebranding of Ticketless Parking

Software Engineer @ Linovi

Izmir, Turkey / 10-2013 to 10-2016

- Began part-time, gaining experience in web development, backend development, and Scala
- Transitioned to full-time in Shazam Team, working on the Self-Service Campaign Management Portal
- Started by writing tests, moved on to developing new features, fixing bugs, and maintaining CI/CD and build systems
- Achieved a significant impact by reducing build times by 50%